<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aaron's rod blossoming, or, The orthodox government of the Church of England by bishops, presbiters, and deacons, asserted from the practice of the apostles, the testimony of councils, synods, fathers and doctors, from the apostles time to this day ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A43</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22486</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12489062</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12489062</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62330</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26279)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62330)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 302:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aaron's rod blossoming, or, The orthodox government of the Church of England by bishops, presbiters, and deacons, asserted from the practice of the apostles, the testimony of councils, synods, fathers and doctors, from the apostles time to this day ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Butler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Epistle dedicatory signed: Basiphilaos.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62330:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62330:1"/>
            <p>AARONS ROD Bloſſoming: <hi>Or,</hi> The Orthodox Government of the Church of <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Biſhops, Presbiters,</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> Aſſerted, from the <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> the <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> of <hi>Councils, Synods, Fathers</hi> and <hi>Doctors,</hi> from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time to this day: And that it is <hi>Analogical</hi> to the Inſtitution of the <hi>Church</hi> under the <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>And thou ſhalt write <hi>Aaron's</hi> Name upon the Rod of <hi>Levi,</hi> for one Rod ſhall be for the Houſe of the Head of their Fathers.</p>
               <p>And it ſhall come to paſs that the Mans Rod whom I ſhall chooſe ſhall Bloſſom, and I will make to ceaſe from me the Murmurings of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whereby they Murmure againſt you,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Numb. 17.3, 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Butler,</hi> next door to the <hi>Holy-Lamb</hi> and <hi>Three Bowls</hi> in <hi>Barbican.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62330:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62330:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the Honourable <hi>CONYERS D'ARCY,</hi> Onely Son of the Right Honourable <hi>CONYERS</hi> Lord <hi>D'ARCY MEYNILL</hi> and <hi>CONYERS.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourable SIR:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not my Ambition, nor was it ever my Deſire to appear in Print, but was always of your <hi>Honours</hi> Opinion for that, and did ever then think my ſelf moſt ſecure, when moſt private: Nor had I now expoſed this to the publick view, had not the duty I owe my too much Diſhonoured Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Importunities of ſome Friends, and the great deſire I had to ſhew your <hi>Honour</hi> ſome Fruit of the Vine your <hi>Honour</hi> hath preſerved, like ſo many
<pb facs="tcp:62330:3"/>perſwading Orators prevailed with me, to preſent your <hi>Honour</hi> with this <hi>Cluſtre,</hi> by the ſmalneſs whereof your <hi>Honour</hi> may well gueſs the Soyl to be a Wilderneſs wherein it grew. I muſt confeſs my repentance is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to arreſt my deſign, when I conſider the ſmall proportion the <hi>Preſent</hi> carries to your <hi>Honours</hi> Greatneſs, till I call to mind, that Heaven it ſelf delights to have her name ſung though from the mouths of <hi>Infancy</hi> and <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance:</hi> and, that ſmall things do oft ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the greatneſs of devotion; and though your <hi>Honours Piety, Charity,</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> (whereof the whole Fame of your <hi>Honours</hi> Countrey is but one entire <hi>Panagyrick</hi>) may render your <hi>Honour</hi> the Admiration of this Age, yet I here intend an <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> not an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comium,</hi> leſt I betray the ſhallowneſs of my Judgment, in offering to draw an imperfect Coppy in a place where the Original can be its own Orator, and appear with ſo much Luſtre.</p>
            <p>It is from hence I receive my Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:62330:3"/>to commit this Orphant to your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> Protection: For, though it be already Legitimated and Licenſed by the <hi>Right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend</hi> the <hi>Lord Biſhop</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> yet I think it fit in theſe <hi>Seducing</hi> and <hi>Apoſtatiſing</hi> Times, to <hi>Patronage</hi> it <hi>with</hi> as much <hi>Virtue</hi> as I could, that under the name of two ſuch God-Fathers, it might with leſs ſcruple paſs for a good <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I humbly therefore implore your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> acceptance thereof from him who will be ever ready to approve himſelf an obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Son of this Orthodox Church, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in nothing more, than in being by your <hi>Honour</hi> eſteemed</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The Humbleſt of your</hi> Honours <hi>Votaries Baſiphilaos.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62330:4"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THou mayeſt, perhaps, wonder at my fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and confidence to hold a Candle to the Sun, and imploy my Time and Pen on a Subject that hath been ſo copiouſly and curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly handled by ſeveral Worthies of this and precedent Ages, eminent for Piety and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Giants in both in compariſon of my ſelf: For which I have only this Apolagy, that this was at firſt intended for my own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſatisfaction; but, the frequent Importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of ſome Worthy and Learned Perſons, after ſome ſtrugling, (I being ever averſe to popularity) have prevailed with me to make it publick, in reſpect of its brevity, whereby many, who have neither Time nor Money to expend upon larger Volumnes, may, I hope, receive ſo
<pb facs="tcp:62330:4"/>much ſatisfaction at leaſt from this ſhort Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, as to ſtay their Stomachs, and keep them from rebellion in theſe ſeducing times (which is commonly the Child ef <hi>Ignorance, Ambition, Prejudice,</hi> or <hi>miſguided Devotion.</hi> And it is probable, the more Curious may find ſomething that hath been omitted by others: For though a Gyant may ſee further than another Man, yet ſet a Dwarf upon a Gyants Shoulder, and he may ſee further than he.</p>
            <p>I confeſs the too violent Contentions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes of Eminent, Learned, and Pious Men of both ſides upon this Subject, cauſed me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline both, for fear of being biaſſed by either, and apply my ſelf to the Fountain of Scripture and Antiquity, Reaſons ſureſt Guides.</p>
            <p>Pruning, I muſt confeſs, and Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I allow of, but Eradication and Deformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I tremble to hear of, and hope never to ſee: God forbid that perſonal Errours ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy a thing ſo Ancient, and ſealed with the Blood of ſo many Martyrs. Though <hi>Judas</hi> die in the Conſciouſneſs of his Treaſon, yet an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb facs="tcp:62330:5"/>muſt ſucceed him in his <hi>Biſhoprick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I endeavour to croud as much as I can in a little room, yet hope to ſatisfie all, who are not more addicted to their Wills than Reaſon (if mine deceive me not) for I look upon <hi>Grave obſtinacy, Pride, formal Ignorance,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Credulity</hi> to be my onely Gainſayers) however I have hereby diſcharged the Duty I owe my Conſcience, and hope to find the benefit of that, which is all I look for; and ſufficient to arm me againſt the Obloquies or Miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of thoſe, whoſe Hearts are full of that which their Tongues muſt utter, or break with the <hi>Plerophory:</hi> But I had rather ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Cenſure of the Malevolent, than to be thought to conſent to that which my Conſcience approves not; if this excuſe me for writing, I am glad; if not, I have pleaſed my ſelf in giving an account of thus much of my Faith to the World, and in the diſcharge of my troubled Thoughts and Conſcience.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62330:5"/>
            <head>AARONS ROD Bloſſoming: <hi>Or,</hi> The Orthodox Government of the Church of <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Biſhops, Presbiters,</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> Aſſerted, from the <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IN Diſcourſes <hi>Rhetorical,</hi> men deſire to ſhew the Power of <hi>Nature,</hi> improved by <hi>Art;</hi> which we call <hi>Eloquence;</hi> in <hi>Logical</hi> Diſputes, the quickneſs of <hi>Apprehenſion,</hi> and the improvement of <hi>Judgement:</hi> the one often makes a difference betwixt <hi>Subtilties,</hi> and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to puzzle <hi>Reaſon:</hi> The other (rightly imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) defines and ſettles a Truth obſcured by different Falſities. In matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> we lay aſide <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and yield to Scripture's Truth, as other Faculties of the Body do to their Informer the <hi>Rational Soul;</hi> and, as Young Scholars to their <hi>ipſe dixits:</hi> We believe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62330:6"/>what neither Sence nor Reaſon can make us to conceive.</p>
            <p>I believe the Scripture to be the Sacred Word of God: and what Truth I find therein, I conceive it to be <hi>Jure Divino:</hi> My Reaſon, I confeſs, is bound, and yields in the Point of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> that it is <hi>Jure Divino;</hi> becauſe I find for it ſo many <hi>ipſe dixits</hi> in Sacred Writ: My Judgement alſo is further ſtrengthened therein, by Reaſons ſufficient to ſettle Humane Belief.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Opinion,</hi> we define to be <hi>haerens &amp; dubia de veritate in animo preſumptio,</hi> a queſtionable and doubtful preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ones conceit that a Matter is true: And <hi>Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio eſt rerum conceptarum per experientiam ſcientia:</hi> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is a ſure Apprehenſion of the Matters we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by experience of their Cauſes and undoubted Grounds of Truth: And <hi>Reſolutio,</hi> is <hi>dubii depoſitio,</hi> the abandoning of all Doubting. I am paſt <hi>Opinion;</hi> and acknowledge my ſelf ſatisfied and well reſolved, that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> and endeavour to give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof in this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>I will not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, withſtand or reſiſt; or ſeek Evaſions or ſubtil Anſwers to evade or elude Gods Truth: Nor do I love <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to be in Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence: Having well weighed the Truth here aſſerted, I find cauſe to ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Great is the force of Truth, and hath prevailed: And to ſatisfie the World what Reaſon I have for this my Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, I leave a Teſtimony thereof in this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>I therefore define <hi>Epiſcopum</hi> to be, <hi>Presbiterum cum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditamento
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62330:6"/>ſuperioritatis quoad regimen in Eccleſia:</hi> A <hi>Biſhop</hi> to be a <hi>Presbiter,</hi> having an Addition of <hi>Superiority,</hi> for the Governing of Gods Church. His Charge is to O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſee the Clergy, and their Flocks; the Word, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, in a large ſignification, may be taken for a <hi>Major</hi> of a <hi>City;</hi> in <hi>Homer, Ajax</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> or Orderer of his Army: But our <hi>Epiſcopus, eſt cleri &amp; gregis in ſua dioceſi,</hi> is Overſeer of his Clergy and Flock bounded within his own Dioceſs: He is alſo <hi>Presbiter,</hi> an <hi>Antient,</hi> and therefore Experienced and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to inform and direct.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Inferiour Presbiter</hi> or <hi>Ancient,</hi> and <hi>Diaconus, Miniſter,</hi> or <hi>Servant,</hi> they are diſtinct and <hi>ſubordinate</hi> to the <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Superiour Preſbiter,</hi> both in the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and in the Practice of the firſt <hi>Century,</hi> and in all Ages even to this Day. Let it not trouble any man, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſometimes term themſelves and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> by the Title of <hi>Presbiters:</hi> they call themſelves alſo <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aconos, Deacons,</hi> in a general Notion: our <hi>Presbiteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> would have <hi>Biſhops</hi> to be, <hi>paſtores jure divi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, praeſides jure eccleſiaſtice; principes jure hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>no &amp; diabolico;</hi> Paſtors by Gods Law; Preſidents by Eccleſiaſtical Law; Lords by Humane and Diabolical Law: How little ground they have for this, let my enſuing Diſcourſe teſtifie.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Biſhop</hi> is a <hi>Presbiter,</hi> or Ancient Paſtor ſet in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent ſuperiority over the Clergy and their Flocks, with relation to the Government of them in Matters <hi>Eccleſiaſtical;</hi> and <hi>ſuch,</hi> I ſay, the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> inſtituted, and to them gave a Charge how to demean themſelves, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62330:7"/>perpetual Succeſſion whereof by practice hath conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued from Chriſts Time to this Day.</p>
            <p>Now for <hi>jus divinum,</hi> I take that to be of Divine Right, which is warranted in Sacred Scripture <hi>de cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendis &amp; agendis,</hi> in matters to be believed, and done: Let this ſerve for the preſent; it will be more enlarged occaſionally in ſome part of this Treatiſe: Only here I add, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Practice of the Apoſtles, which never was queſtioned, and excepted againſt, and is recorded in the Canonical Scripture, hath in it a <hi>jus divinum,</hi> and ſhews what is of Divine Right <hi>de facto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things premiſed, I proceed to Objections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my Aſſertion, and anſwer them particularly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Eminent Superiority and Lordly Authority over the People, is that which the Lords of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> may, and do challenge, and practice as their due <hi>jure humano,</hi> by Humane Right, and therefore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by the Law of things oppoſite. Eminent Superiority, and Lordly Authority over the Clergy and People of God, is that which Biſhops ought not to challenge or practice <hi>jure divino;</hi> For Proof they bring. <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.25, 26. The Princes of the <hi>Gentiles dominantur, Lord</hi> it, and Rule over them; but you, <hi>non ſic:</hi> Or, it ſhall not be ſo with you. And the 1 of <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>Feed the Flock of the Lord, taking the Overſight thereof; not by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, but willingly; not churliſhly, or covetouſly for filthy Lucre, but of a ready Mind; neither as being Lords over Gods Heritage.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62330:7"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I Anſwer, That the Meaſure of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination not the Matter, lies in the word, <hi>ſic;</hi> and ſo is expounded by the other words, not by conſtraint, but willingly; not churliſhly, or covetouſly; not as though ye were Lords dominering over them, but that ye may be Enſamples to the Flock: <hi>Non herile aut regale imperium exercentes, ſed paſtorali ſuperioritate &amp; pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na gubernatione utentes:</hi> Not exerciſing a Maſter-like or Kingly Command, but uſing a Paſtoral Superiority, and Fatherly Government: And ſo this rather (as I conceive) confirms <hi>Superiority</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys it: For the word, <hi>ſic,</hi> ſo, takes not away the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality, but qualifies the Power given, by ſaying, (nay commanding) let it be uſed, <hi>ſic,</hi> ſo; which I prove to be the meaning of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> by this Argument.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> is not contrary to Chriſts and their own <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and the <hi>Sence</hi> thereof; but the <hi>Apostles</hi> did practice <hi>Eminent Superiority,</hi> and ſuch law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority as Chriſt forbids not, over the Clergy and Flock, and inſtituted <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> therefore their <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> allowed the ſame: And ſo, that cannot be meant by the words above, which is pretended, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That there ſhould be a <hi>Parity</hi> in the Clergy; and that <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy</hi> is <hi>Dominium in Clerum,</hi> a Lordly Rule over the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an uſurped Authority.</p>
            <p>The Succeſſors which they inſtituted, are warranted by Chriſt when he ſaid, <hi>I am with you to the end of the World:</hi> that is, I am with you, while you live, and with <hi>Succeſſors</hi> in your ſtead, governing and teaching
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62330:8"/>the Church to the Worlds end. Hence it was, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ordained <hi>Biſhops</hi> to ſucceed them: So did the <hi>ancient Fathers</hi> in the purer times; and this Courſe hath continued ever ſince.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Apostles</hi> was in <hi>ſuperiority</hi> over o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Clergy: and to the <hi>Biſhops</hi> whom they conſtituted to ſucceed themſelves in place over the Clergy, they gave a <hi>ſuperior authority:</hi> Neither did they either practice, or ever mention that <hi>parity</hi> in power, which the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> ſo much endeavour to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce: And therefore the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> never underſtood the words as theſe men do, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that they ſhould diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of <hi>Biſhops</hi> in <hi>ſuperior authority</hi> above other of the Clergy.</p>
            <p>To make the Practice of the <hi>Apostles</hi> evident, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to <hi>Paul,</hi> who gave to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus Epiſcopal</hi> Power, to the one in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> to the other in <hi>Creet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to clear this, let us firſt oleanſe the Spring-Head, and then the Streams will run clear down to after-times. I have, above, to this end, defined <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum,</hi> if we obſerve what he is, then ſhall we evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſee, whether St. <hi>Paul</hi> did inſtitute ſuch a <hi>Calling</hi> or no.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Civil Biſhops</hi> I ſpeak not, but of <hi>Spiritual;</hi> and a <hi>Biſhop</hi> of this kind, <hi>I</hi> defined to be, <hi>presbiterum, cum addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamento ſuperioritatis, quoad regimen in eccleſia:</hi> He governs the Clergy and their Flocks in Spiritual matters: <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> of this kind St. <hi>Paul</hi> did inſtitute; he made <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> and <hi>Titus Epiſcopos Cleri &amp; gregis quoad regimen in eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia;</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62330:8"/>Biſhops of the Clergy and their Flocks, and to have <hi>Eccleſiastical Government</hi> over them; whereas, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they were but <hi>Presbyters,</hi> or <hi>Diſciples,</hi> brought up under him; by this Inſtitution were other <hi>Presbyters</hi> made ſubordinate to them, in governing and teaching the Church: which to prove, <hi>I</hi> thus argue.</p>
            <p>He that is ordained, and <hi>ſo</hi> ordained, that he hath power <hi>constituere presbiteros per civitates,</hi> to ordain Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ters in every City, is greater than thoſe, who have no ſuch power in their Cities and Churches; and they who may correct what is defective are <hi>ſuperior</hi> to thoſe, for whom matters defective are corrected: but <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> had ſuch power given them, and did ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect things defective, and none of the <hi>Presbyters</hi> had the ſame from the <hi>Apostles,</hi> (no not <hi>Timothy</hi> nor <hi>Titus</hi> whilſt onely <hi>Presbyters</hi>) therefore I conclude undeniably, that <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were <hi>Superiors,</hi> as <hi>Biſhops,</hi> over the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> in their ſeveral Charges and Diviſions, <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Creet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That they had this Power given them by <hi>Paul,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.22. <hi>Lay hands ſuddainly on no man. Tit.</hi> 1.5. <hi>For this cauſe I left thee in</hi> Creet, <hi>that thou ſhould'ſt ſet in order, things which were wanting, and</hi> ordain Elders <hi>in every City, as I had appointed thee.</hi> If any other in thoſe Churches could have ordained <hi>Presbyters,</hi> why was <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> ſent to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> left at <hi>Creet</hi> for this very purpoſe? And if the <hi>Cretians</hi> could have ſet in order things defective, what need was there that <hi>Titus</hi> alone ſhould have this Commiſſion?</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:62330:9"/>
            <p> St. <hi>Jerom</hi> (no great Friend to <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi>) gives us in his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to <hi>Evagrius,</hi> pag. 329, this as a Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, remarkable, betwixt a <hi>Biſhop</hi> and a <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> ſaying, <hi>quid facit, excepta ordinatione, Epiſcopus, quod non facit Presbiter:</hi> What does a Biſhop, except the Ordaining of Others, which a <hi>Presbyter</hi> does not? And it is worth the obſervation, what the Antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Champion for the Bleſſed Trinity, <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> hath in his <hi>Second Apologie, (viz.)</hi> That <hi>Colithus,</hi> a <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biter</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> had conſtituted <hi>Presbyters;</hi> But what became of them? <hi>Reciſſa eſt haec ejus ordinatio, &amp; omnes ab eo conſtituti, in</hi> Laicorum <hi>ordinem redacti fuere:</hi> The or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining of others by him, was made invalid, and they who were ordained by him, were degraded and made <hi>Laicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then you ſee, that <hi>Biſhops</hi> are <hi>Eminenter ſuperiores presbiteris;</hi> Eminently ſuperiour to Presbyters, having power affirmative and negative, by the <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Antient Fathers.</hi> This confirmes what the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had taught and practiſed, and appointed others in place above the ordinary <hi>Presbyters</hi> to do.</p>
            <p>Now I come to ſhew the Second Difference betwixt a <hi>Biſhop</hi> and a <hi>Presbyter:</hi> And wherein a <hi>Biſhop</hi> hath <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minentem ſuperioritatem,</hi> a clear Superiority above a <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter:</hi> that is, in <hi>Excommunication;</hi> which was called <hi>Mucro Epiſcopalis,</hi> the Epiſcopal Weapon; and was a Power given to <hi>Biſhops Succeſſors</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and was ever practiſed by them: This appears, in that, an Account of it was, and is expected at their hands; as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62330:9"/>it is manifeſted by the quarrel, which our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour had againſt the <hi>Angel</hi> of the Church of <hi>Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> namely, that he ſuffered ſome of his Church, who held the Doctrine of the <hi>Nicholaitans;</hi> and againſt the Angel of the Church of <hi>Thiatira,</hi> that he ſuffered the woman <hi>Jeſabel</hi> to teach and ſeduce the people: By this it is apparent, that Chriſt expected they ſhould do what they had by their places power to do; namely, that they being Angels of their Churches, (whom I affirm to be alſo Biſhops thereof, and Succeſſors to the Apoſtles, as is ſufficiently proved by the moſt reverend and learned <hi>Archbiſhop of Armagh,</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> himſelf, calling them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> men in place above others) ſhould <hi>Hereticos coercere &amp; ex Eccleſia ejicere,</hi> keep under Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and caſt them out of the Church.</p>
            <p>If here it be objected, that we muſt not argue from dark and myſtical places of Scripture, ſuch as is the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalypſe:</hi> I anſwer, that I argue from a plain place, and from the plain words and direct Scope of the place; and not from the myſtical Sence or Interpretation, neither can we here admit of that diſtinction, that <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelus</hi> is in this place to be taken <hi>Collectively, pro tota Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia</hi> for the whole Church: For, I conceive, there is not a word in Scripture but hath its weight: and was it not as eaſy to have ſaid <hi>Eccleſiae,</hi> as <hi>Angelo Eceleſiae,</hi> if <hi>Angelo</hi> had not ſomething more in it then <hi>Eccleſiae?</hi> and why not <hi>Angelus Eccleſia</hi> the Angel the Church? but <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelus Eccleſiae</hi> the Angel of the Church, if it had been to be taken <hi>Collectively?</hi> but the terms are different, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62330:10"/>of a diſtinct force, like thoſe <hi>panis Domin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the bread of the Lord: and <hi>panis Dominus,</hi> bread repreſenting the Lord.</p>
            <p>Beſides, to come to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to command others <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not to teach other Doctrine: and <hi>obturaro ora deceptorum &amp; hereticos rejicere:</hi> to ſtop the mouths of deceivers, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject Hereticks: theſe things were commanded them, and an Account accordingly expected of the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance thereof, which manifeſtly proves, that every Church had its <hi>Angelum,</hi> who had <hi>Epiſcopal Authority</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> eminent above other inferiour Clergy-men, and not many <hi>Angels</hi> in each of theſe Churches, all of equal Authority and place: or, at leaſt, the <hi>Angel</hi> in each of the ſeven Churches, was ſo abſolute in his power, that he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Chief Governour; the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters</hi> only <hi>Aſſiſtants</hi> to him: he a <hi>Spiritual Juſtice;</hi> and of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> they of the <hi>Council.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The difference alſo of <hi>Epiſcopal Authority</hi> from that of <hi>Bresbyters,</hi> appears in the Cauſe of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> where there was an Appeal to the Synods, which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirmed or diſolved them, but none to the <hi>People,</hi> none to the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> this is confirmed by the antient <hi>Council</hi> at <hi>Nice,</hi> Can. 5. and at <hi>Antioch,</hi> Can. 6. and <hi>Jerom</hi> himſelf writing to <hi>Riparius</hi> concerning <hi>Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius,</hi> an heretical <hi>Presbyter,</hi> is angry, that the Biſhop under whom he was, did <hi>acquieſcere ejus furori, &amp; non virga Apoſtolica, virgaque ferrea, vas inutile confringere, &amp; tradere ad interitum Carnis, ut ſpiritus ſalvus fiat,</hi> did
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62330:10"/>quietly give way to his fury, and not rather break in pieces that unprofitable veſſel with his <hi>Apoſtolick Staff</hi> and rod of Iron, and deliver him up to the deſtruction of the Fleſh, that his Soul might be ſaved.</p>
            <p>And it ſeems ſtrange to me, that any ſhould think, that our Bleſſed Saviour his Executioners, Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators, and Aſſigns, knew not the meaning of his <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Teſtament,</hi> as well as we in theſe days. Chriſt, who aſcending to Heaven, gave Gifts to many, would not deny this Gift ſo neceſſary: He, I ſay, giving ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereminent Gifts to the <hi>Apoſtles ad fundandam eccleſiam,</hi> for the founding of his Church; would not deny to their <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> thoſe which were neceſſary <hi>eccleſiae fundatae,</hi> to the Church being founded: and ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that nothing more concerns the Church. Would he not, or could he not inform his Truſtees how he pleaſed to have his Church (his Houſhold) governed in his abſence? To ſay he would not, is derogatory to his Wiſdom, and Goodneſs; to ſay he could not, to his Almighty Sovereign Power.</p>
            <p>I therefore conclude theſe Points;</p>
            <p>Firſt, That <hi>Ordination</hi> of <hi>Presbyters,</hi> was left to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> as to men of higher place and <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and not to the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> who were of inferior Degree.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Power given to the <hi>Angels</hi> of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> and the other Churches, puts a difference of <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority</hi> betwixt a <hi>Biſhop</hi> and an ordinary <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and other the Teachers of the Churches, and gives them
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62330:11"/>commiſſion <hi>prae ceteris tam Clericis, quam Laicis;</hi> above others, both Clergy, and Laity, yea a coercive and caſtigative Power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Further they object, That <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is not <hi>jure divino,</hi> becauſe Chriſt did not command it in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I anſwer, That <hi>jus divinum aliter in ſe habet in credendis, aliter in agendis:</hi> There is a difference of divine Right in matters to be believed, and matters to be done. In matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> there muſt be <hi>textus manifeſtus, aut convincens deductio;</hi> a <hi>clear Text,</hi> or a <hi>ſound Conſequence.</hi> As for example, <hi>(In the beginning God made all things)</hi> that is <hi>textus manifeſtus;</hi> but there is onely <hi>convincens deductio</hi> concerning the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of the bleſſed <hi>Trinity,</hi> which is only proved thus:</p>
            <p>There came down at Chriſts Baptiſm, the <hi>Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> in the form of a <hi>Dove;</hi> and a voice was heard, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed:</hi> Here we find the Spirit in the form of a <hi>Dove;</hi> there is heard a <hi>voice,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſeen in the <hi>water,</hi> we know by the light of <hi>Scripture.</hi> and the light of <hi>Nature,</hi> that there is but <hi>one God;</hi> and that from <hi>one,</hi> all things are, and that in <hi>one</hi> they terminate. And that there is <hi>aliud medium, copulans primum &amp; ultimum, one between both, coup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the first and the laſt.</hi> Seeing alſo we read that there is a <hi>Father,</hi> a <hi>Son,</hi> and a <hi>Spirit,</hi> and that there is but <hi>one God:</hi> We hence infer, by <hi>neceſſary deduction,</hi> that there are <hi>three perſons,</hi> and but <hi>one God;</hi> Beſides, this deduction is further confirmed by that Text, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62330:11"/>
               <hi>Theſe three are one;</hi> which, in ſome ſort, is <hi>textus mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtus,</hi> a clear Text.</p>
            <p>Now a Matter of Fact may be inferred to be <hi>jure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino,</hi> as I ſuppoſe, if I prove,
<list>
                  <item>1. Firſt, That the ſame Fact was the <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Secondly, that it is <hi>Analogical</hi> to the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which was ſettled according to Gods <hi>Appointment,</hi> by the <hi>Mediation</hi> of <hi>Angels,</hi> by the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Thirdly, That it is pointed at, and <hi>inſinuated,</hi> in the <hi>New-Teſtament.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. Fourthly, That it hath <hi>ſucceſſively</hi> continued ſince the <hi>Apoſtles time,</hi> as elſewhere, ſo particularly in <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe points can be proved concerning the <hi>Fact</hi> in queſtion, <hi>(viz.) Government</hi> by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> I hope none will deny it to be <hi>jure divino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for Proof and Confirmation, that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is <hi>jure divino;</hi> I will prove theſe Points, and then ſay ſomething concerning the Practice of other Churches.</p>
            <p>And firſt; St. <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> and <hi>Dr.</hi> of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> gave Power and Authority to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus, ordinare dignos,</hi> to ordain men worthy, and to examine ſuch as were faulty; to reprove and diſcharge ſuch as were guilty, and did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, teach other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and were offenſive to the honour of their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and to cheriſh ſuch as did well. Thoſe things are evident in the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62330:12"/>that to <hi>Titus:</hi> From <hi>Pauls</hi> Practice of <hi>Superiority</hi> over theſe two, and from the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> to be <hi>Biſhops,</hi> I prove <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> to be practiſed by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> to make which good, I thus argue:</p>
            <p>If St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf practiſed eminent <hi>ſuperiority,</hi> and, in the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> alledged, gave all that <hi>power</hi> which of right <hi>Biſhops</hi> challenge, or doth belong to the definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> then <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf did not only practice <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> but did alſo <hi>Conſtitute</hi> them <hi>Biſhops;</hi> but <hi>verum prius, ergo &amp; poſterius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That he had <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> as the other <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> had, ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 1.20. and did diligently run his courſe therein, no man will deny; and that he gave Power to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> the ſame which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had;
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To Ordain,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>to Puniſh,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>to Convent,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>to Reward duplici honore,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> with double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the Epiſtles alledged do ſufficiently prove: Therefore <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf practiſed <hi>ſuperiority,</hi> and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus Biſhops</hi> in place <hi>ſuperiour</hi> to <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters,</hi> whom they had Authority to <hi>Ordain, Convent,</hi> and <hi>Puniſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If they object, That <hi>Presbyters</hi> with a <hi>Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> may do the ſame, even all things which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus;</hi> and therefore theſe things were ſpoken to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> and to their <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Collectively,</hi> in the Perſons of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62330:12"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, Their Old Friend <hi>(Collectively)</hi> will do them as little good here, as elſewhere; for this is but <hi>petere principium,</hi> an Evaſion which I have formerly taken away: And now, further I argue, Such as the Charge is, ſuch is the Power; but the <hi>Charge</hi> is <hi>perſonal</hi> that is given to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> particularly, and therefore the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> given, is <hi>perſonal;</hi> to them for their time, and to their <hi>Succeſſours</hi> in place after them; and not to them, and the <hi>Presbytery Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively;</hi> nothing in place where ſuch Charge is given, doth intimate the <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>Deacons</hi> interpoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in theſe <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Actions with <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus;</hi> If they will have theſe Priviledges and Performances to belong to their <hi>Preſident;</hi> they muſt plead them due to him as he is <hi>Succeſſor</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> and ſo he is in effect (if you give him <hi>Continuance</hi> in his place) a <hi>Biſhop</hi> indeed: The bare Name of a <hi>Preſident</hi> cannot make him of a different Calling from a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> whenas he acteth the part of a Biſhop in all thoſe points by St. <hi>Paul</hi> preſcribed. The Practice of all times (eſpecially the firſt <hi>Century</hi>) warrants not a <hi>Monthly</hi> or <hi>Yearly Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> doing nothing for <hi>Ordination, Convention, Puniſhment,</hi> and <hi>Reward,</hi> without the <hi>Adviſe</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Presbyters:</hi> But it allows <hi>Biſhops Superiority</hi> to <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi> to <hi>Deacons;</hi> yea it placed <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Succeſſours</hi> to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> as were <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus;</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons ſubordinate</hi> to <hi>Biſhops</hi> as to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> whilſt the lived.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> the next <hi>Biſhop</hi> to <hi>Evodius,</hi> he received
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62330:13"/>
               <hi>Epiſcopal Charge</hi> from the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> and writing to them at <hi>Antioch,</hi> when he was carried Priſoner to <hi>Rome,</hi> he uſes theſe words to the <hi>Laity, Obſequium prebete presbyteris, &amp; Diaconis;</hi> be ye obedient to your <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons;</hi> and addeth to the <hi>Presbyters, paſcite gregem apud vos, donec Deus oſtendit</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, feed the Flock under you, until God ſhew who ſhall be your <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour:</hi> and hereby eſtabliſhes <hi>Superiority</hi> to <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and enjoyns the <hi>Presbyters Obedience.</hi> The ſame Father in an Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> acknowledgeth <hi>Oneſſimus,</hi> (named often by <hi>Paul</hi>) to be their <hi>Biſhop;</hi> and exhorts them, ſaying, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as it becomes you, ſubmit your ſelves to your <hi>Biſhops</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: Thus here we find St. <hi>Pauls Charge</hi> or <hi>Ordination</hi> obſerved and followed by <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who lived in the firſt <hi>Century,</hi> and whoſe Worth and Authority clouds of Witneſſes do confirm.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Journey he writes to the Church of <hi>Smir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and ſalutes their <hi>Biſhop</hi> by name, and exhorts the Flock, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; to follow their <hi>Biſhop,</hi> as Jeſus Chriſt did his <hi>Father;</hi> and the <hi>Presbytery</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> The <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> here ſpoken of was <hi>Policarpus;</hi> as <hi>Ireneus</hi> his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, affirms; <hi>&amp; multa accepit ab illo de ſancti</hi> Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis <hi>vita &amp; converſatione;</hi> Cotemporary with <hi>Ireneus,</hi> and by whom he was informed in many things concerning St. <hi>John</hi>'s Life and Converſation.</p>
            <p>In the life time of <hi>Trajan</hi> the Emperour, St. <hi>John</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning from his Baniſhment out of <hi>Patmos,</hi> where he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62330:13"/>wrote the <hi>Revelations,</hi> ſummoned the Seven <hi>Biſhops,</hi> (who are conceived to be thoſe named in the <hi>Apocalips</hi> the <hi>Angels</hi> of the Seven Churches) and uſed their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry for ſetling and ordering his own Metropolis of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> and the other Churches in <hi>Aſia;</hi> (as the antient <hi>Greek</hi> Records, found in the Library of <hi>Photius,</hi> teſtifie) Concerning this <hi>Apoſtolical Superiority,</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and <hi>Ordination</hi> of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> is frequent men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Ireneus, Euſebius,</hi> and <hi>Jerom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that by that which hath been ſaid, we ſee, that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, warranted by the <hi>practice</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> becauſe that <hi>viventibus, conſtituentibus, &amp; confirmantibus Apoſtolis; &amp; viris Apoſtolicis, patribus &amp; docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus teſtantibus;</hi> The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> men being alive; ſeing it, appointing it and confirming it; and the <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Doctors</hi> being eye-witneſſes thereof, there were theſe <hi>three diſtinct Degrees</hi> in the <hi>Clergy,</hi> (viz.) <hi>Biſhops, Presbyters, Deacons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to the Second Point, That <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is <hi>Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical</hi> to the Inſtitution of the Church <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Old <hi>Teſtament,</hi> which <hi>Moſes,</hi> as a <hi>Prince,</hi> did eſtabliſh by Gods appointment in the Wilderneſs, and which continued in force, till the Veil of the Temple rent, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> became Heirs to <hi>Abraham:</hi> And the Promiſes made to him, were made good to us his Heirs by <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Adoption:</hi> Becauſe the <hi>Jews, Abrahams</hi> Heirs according to the Fleſh, by their own default and diſobedience, forfeited their Intereſt in that Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Inheritance which they claimed from their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62330:14"/>
               <hi>Abraham,</hi> by the Evidences regiſtred in <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets: Epiſcopacy</hi> and Subordination thereto, I ſay, holds <hi>Analogy</hi> and a kind of proportion of the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh-Church-Government;</hi> for God, in it, appointed an <hi>High-Prieſt, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Levites, ſubordinate</hi> one to the other; ſuch is the <hi>Subordination</hi> of the <hi>three Degrees</hi> in the Clergy. In the <hi>New-Teſtament-Church,</hi> St. <hi>Jerom</hi> near the end of his Epiſtle to <hi>Evagrius,</hi> obſerves, and ſays, <hi>ſcimus traditiones Apoſtolorum ſumptas de veteri Testamento, quod</hi> Aaron <hi>&amp; filii ejus at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> Levitae <hi>in templo fuere, Hoc E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopi, Presbiteri, &amp; Diaconi ſibi vindicant in Eccleſia ſcil. Chriſtiana:</hi> The Orders delivered to the Church by the Apoſtles, were taken out of the <hi>Old Teſtament;</hi> the ſame Subordination which was in <hi>Aaron,</hi> his Sons, and the <hi>Levites,</hi> now appear in the Chriſtian Church, in our <hi>Biſhops, Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Deacons.</hi> This proportion is made undeniable by St. <hi>Jude,</hi> who Charges ſome in the Chriſtian Church, with the <hi>Gainſaying</hi> of <hi>Korah;</hi> now there can be no gainſaying like that of <hi>Korah</hi> in the Chriſtian Church, except there be <hi>diſtinction</hi> and <hi>ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> of <hi>Superiours</hi> and <hi>Inferiours</hi> in the <hi>Clergy,</hi> as there was in <hi>Korah</hi>'s time, and was gainſaid by him and his Complices, deſirous of <hi>ſuperiour honour,</hi> and of higher degrees and places than they had a Calling unto. Here then you ſee, that God would have a Proportion of Church-Government betwixt the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is further worthy the obſervation, that both the Church and Common-wealth of the <hi>Jews,</hi> had in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62330:14"/>their <hi>Government</hi> a kind of <hi>proportion eſtabliſht by God:</hi> For the <hi>Church</hi> was <hi>Monarchical</hi> in <hi>Aaron; Aristocratical</hi> in ſome Select <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites;</hi> ſo was the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth Monarchical</hi> in <hi>Moſes: Aristocratical in ſome Select Princes</hi> of each Tribe governing under <hi>Moſes;</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocratical</hi> in the reſt, and in the whole Body of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And ſuch is the <hi>proportion</hi> betwixt our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and ſuch hath it been from the firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; this will, I hope appear when I come to ſpeak of the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> in our <hi>Church;</hi> and what kind of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> thus ſuitable to that of the <hi>Jews,</hi> is in any one <hi>Church,</hi> may be in all <hi>Churches;</hi> namely; all degrees of men ſubordinate to their <hi>Princes,</hi> and all <hi>Princes</hi> or <hi>Kings, ſubordinate to Christ,</hi> without having any King on earth Head over the reſt: As all the degrees of men in the <hi>Churches</hi> were <hi>ſubordinate</hi> to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> going to ſeveral and far remote Nations, were all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually <hi>ſubordinate</hi> to <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude this then, ſeeing the Conſtitution of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal</hi> Government, is ſo agreeable to that which is moſt abſolute, and was eſtabliſht by that Wiſdom, that no other <hi>Common-wealth</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> ever was, (as one obſerves) <hi>dictante Deo, Constituente Moſe,</hi> God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining it, and <hi>Moſes</hi> putting it in Practice, why ſhould any endeavour to alter it? It is held an <hi>Axiome</hi> amongſt <hi>Architectors,</hi> that it is not wiſdom to pull down a main Poſt of a Building, eſpecially ſo antient and well ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled, except we be ſure to ſettle and fix another which is right and fitted to our purpoſe, which yet for all the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62330:15"/>Workmans skill may have a private Flaw in it, which cannot be diſcovered; and ſo may the Building fall on the Builders Heads.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the <hi>Analogie</hi> and Proportion betwixt <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and the Church-Government of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, in the Third place, I come to prove, That <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> was pointed at, and, in ſome ſort, deciphered in the <hi>New-teſtament.</hi> What I produced before concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Authority of <hi>Ordination, Convention, Puniſhment,</hi> and <hi>Reward,</hi> put upon ſome ſpecial perſons, may ſerve ſufficiently to this purpoſe; Yet ſomething more I will here add. Be it ſo, that when the <hi>Apostle</hi> ſays, <hi>If any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Office of a</hi> Biſhop, <hi>he deſires a good work,</hi> that this is ſpoken of an <hi>Inferiour Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Presbiter,</hi> which is an <hi>Overſeer</hi> of the People committed to his charge, as well as of a <hi>Biſhop Superiour,</hi> who hath the overſight of the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>People:</hi> Yet will it follow, that, if the Office of an <hi>Inferiour Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Overſeer</hi> of his Flock be a good Work, (as indeed it is) then much more they who have laboured in that painful Harveſt firſt, and afterward, in their <hi>elder Years,</hi> are advanced to the <hi>Superiour Biſhops Office</hi> of <hi>Overſeeing</hi> the <hi>Clergy,</hi> of <hi>Ordaining, Conventing,</hi> and the like, as aforeſaid, undergo and perform <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a good work of greater eminency and more Notable; for, certainly, there cannot be a more bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Work, nor more holy Calling in the Clergy, than to <hi>ſucceed</hi> the <hi>Glorious Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Martyrs</hi> in their places and callings, as Heirs do their Parents in their Eſtates and Poſſeſſions; and to deliver and teach Sacred. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62330:15"/>to Faithful men, who ſhall be able to teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> bids <hi>Timothy, Tim.</hi> 2.2. To this purpoſe St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> upon the <hi>45th.</hi> Pſal. Thus <hi>Gloſſes, Pro patribus tibi nati ſunt filii,</hi> Children ſhall be inſtead of Fathers; ſaying, <hi>Patres miſſi, ſunt Apoſtoli; pro Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolis filii tibi nati, conſtituti ſunt Epiſcopi; hodie enim Epiſcopi qui ſunt per totum orbem, unde nati ſunt? ipſa eccleſia patres illos appellat, ipſa filios genuit, &amp; ipſa illos conſtituit in ſedibus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum;</hi> the <hi>Fathers</hi> ſent to us were the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> the <hi>Sons</hi> which were appointed, are <hi>Biſhops;</hi> for at this day, the <hi>Biſhops</hi> in all the world, from whence did they ariſe? the Church it ſelf calls them <hi>Fathers; ſhe her ſelf begot</hi> theſe <hi>Sons;</hi> and ſhe her ſelf hath put them into the <hi>Seats</hi> of the <hi>Fathers:</hi> Here you ſee the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> proved plainly by <hi>Austin,</hi> as before by <hi>Ireneus, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius, Ignatius,</hi> and a Cloud of Witneſſes, who ſealed their witneſs with their Blood, and are thoſe whoſe Robes are waſht in the Blood of the <hi>Lamb;</hi> and who ſhall ſhine brighter than the <hi>Cynoſure</hi> amongſt the Stars of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Beſides all the Witneſſes and Proofs already brought, I will produce one Text more to prove <hi>Biſhops</hi> to be <hi>Succeſſours</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles jure divino:</hi> In that Great <hi>Synod, Acts</hi> 1. where were aſſembled the eleven <hi>Diſciples, &amp; fere centum &amp; viginti,</hi> other perſons Believers about an hundred and twenty, St. <hi>Peter</hi> moved the conſideration of an <hi>Election</hi> of one in the place of <hi>Judas,</hi> and urges two places in the <hi>Pſalms</hi> as <hi>Propheſies</hi> which muſt be fulfilled, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.25. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.6. there the <hi>Holy Ghoſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:62330:16"/>by the mouth of <hi>David</hi> concerning <hi>Judas, Let his Habitation be void, and let no man dwell therein:</hi> Not his place only void, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, let ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take his <hi>Biſhoprick.</hi> Mark well the words, and grant we theſe two Aſſertions:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That no man will ſay there is a <hi>tautologie</hi> or <hi>vaniloquium</hi> in the words of Sacred Scripture, or that any word may be altered, or can be bettered.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That the Scriptures ſhould be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as near as we can, <hi>litterally,</hi> and as the plain ſence of the place will bear, and ſo as may ſtand with the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogie</hi> of other Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Theſe things granted, I thus argue:</p>
            <p>That which the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> by the mouth of a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> hath foretold, and the bleſſed <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in a <hi>Synod</hi> have <hi>ratified,</hi> that, I ſay, is an undeniable Truth, and may plead its <hi>jus divinum;</hi> But <hi>David</hi> did foretel, by the Inſpiration of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of Propheſie, that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> ſhould <hi>ſucceed Apostleſhip,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ratified it in their <hi>Synod,</hi> therefore <hi>Epiſcopacy ſucceeded Apoſtleſhip jure divino:</hi> It is not any other word which is attributed to <hi>Matthias</hi>'s Place but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Biſhoprick;</hi> and he <hi>ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Judas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If any here object, That <hi>Matthias</hi> had <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> of <hi>Judas;</hi> ſo that <hi>Judas</hi>'s <hi>Apoſtleſhip,</hi> is there called a <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> in a general notion, as it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports an <hi>Office</hi> or <hi>Charge;</hi> and that therefore <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> did not <hi>ſucceed Apoſtleſhip;</hi> but that both of them were of right attributed to the <hi>Twelve,</hi> choſen by Chriſt,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62330:16"/>and both given to <hi>Matthias</hi> who <hi>ſucceeded Judas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Suppoſe this be granted, it makes much more for what I intend: For firſt, If they be terms of ſo near Affinity, that they ſerve to expreſs one and the ſame Office in a different regard; then it follows, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their Affinity, the one may more eaſily <hi>ſucceed</hi> in the others place: For where there is a likeneſs of <hi>Nature,</hi> there is <hi>facilior tranſitus,</hi> an eaſier <hi>Change</hi> of one thing into another; as of <hi>Air</hi> into <hi>Fire,</hi> becauſe of their agreement in the quality of <hi>heat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Seeing the Term of <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> was by thoſe and after times in ſome ſort appropriate to ſome few, it remained, that the other Term, of <hi>Biſhop,</hi> ſhould be left and turned over to their <hi>Succeſſours;</hi> and with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to this, <hi>Matthias</hi> is expreſly ſaid to <hi>ſucceed</hi> in <hi>Judas</hi>'s <hi>Epiſcopacy:</hi> And the chief Officers of the Clergy are termed <hi>Biſhops,</hi> rather than by any other Name. This we read to have been the conſtant practice of the firſt <hi>Century;</hi> in which (as it is likely) the <hi>Executors</hi> and <hi>Feofees</hi> in truſt of our <hi>Lord,</hi> beſt underſtood the Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Teſtator;</hi> and had Gifts extraordinary <hi>ad ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam &amp; fidem ſtabiliendam,</hi> as to eſtabliſh our <hi>Faith,</hi> ſo the <hi>Church</hi> too, and could beſt fit right terms to <hi>Perſons,</hi> and <hi>Callings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to come cloſe to <hi>our ſelves;</hi> This <hi>Iſland</hi> received Chriſtianity very ſoon, even in the days of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> as <hi>Gildas Brietto</hi> (a grave Authour writeth; who wrote <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 493. And as another <hi>Gildas</hi> after him confirms. This <hi>Gildas</hi> was called <hi>Albanicus,</hi> and (as ſome will
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62330:17"/>have it) preceded the other: He teſtifies, that after the diſperſing of the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> by reaſon of the Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Philip</hi> ſent out of <hi>France, Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others, who preacht the Goſpel in this Kingdom; their Doctrine (as <hi>Malmsbury</hi> hath it) was afterward confirmed by other Preachers, and Doctors here. This is alſo witneſſed both by <hi>Origen,</hi> and <hi>Theodoret;</hi> (not to ſpeak of thoſe, who ſome of them affirm that <hi>Paul</hi> ſome that <hi>Peter,</hi> and ſome that <hi>James</hi> were in this <hi>Iſland,</hi> and viſited the Church here eſtabliſhed; (as <hi>Baronius,</hi> a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Writer,</hi> and of ſpecial note hath it.) It is further ſaid, that <hi>Inſula Glacialis</hi> (which we now call <hi>Glaſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi>) was granted them by <hi>Arviragus,</hi> King of the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,</hi> and that <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea, lived, died,</hi> and was <hi>buried</hi> there: This is atteſted by divers memorable <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords,</hi> alledged by the ſtudious and learned Searchers into the <hi>Brittiſh Antiquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for that report of <hi>Lucius</hi> and <hi>Eleutherius</hi> of <hi>Romes Supremacy,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Beda</hi> and <hi>Marianus Scotus,</hi> and ſo often alledged by divers others; I muſt either think that <hi>Rome</hi> had changed her Cuſtoms and many of her Tenents, or queſtion the Truth of the Relation: My reaſon for this, is, becauſe when in the year 601. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> the <hi>Monk</hi> firſt required <hi>obedience</hi> to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in three things, <hi>(viz.)</hi> in <hi>paſcate celebrando; in baptiſmo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrando; in predicando Anglis Saxonibus:</hi> In <hi>Celebrating Eaſter;</hi> in <hi>Adminiſtring Baptiſm;</hi> in <hi>Preaching</hi> to the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh:</hi> His Motion was refuſed, and <hi>Auſtin</hi> utterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked, <hi>quia</hi> (to uſe the words of another) <hi>Auguſtini fastum
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62330:17"/>ſpernebant,</hi> they diſliked <hi>Austin's</hi> Pride; and well they might, for he was haughty and harſh, and did contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to his Directions from <hi>Gregory Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> who ſent him hither; for he inſenſed <hi>Edelfred,</hi> ſo againſt the poor Chriſtians of <hi>Bangor,</hi> that he put 1200 of them to the Sword; Of this the reaſon is given, <hi>quia noluere obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium Augustino prebere,</hi> becauſe they would not ſubmit to <hi>Auſtin's</hi> Will: For this was indeed the quarrel, as our Writers ſay. This their refuſal to yield to <hi>Auſtin</hi> the <hi>Monk,</hi> I produce as a Proof, that the Chriſtians, which he found here, held in many things with the <hi>Eaſtern Churches,</hi> as having their <hi>Doctrine</hi> from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Sion,</hi> whence the Goſpel was to be ſent, <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Malachi</hi> 4.2. to the Nations; and whence as Salvation went, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.7. ſo likewiſe the Doctrine of Salvation; for Chriſt, who gave the <hi>Apoſtles Commiſſion</hi> to go to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and preach the Goſpel, did bid them ſtay at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> (not at <hi>Rome</hi>) till the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> had furniſht them with Gifts for the work commanded. This further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, by that reſolute Anſwer which the <hi>Abbot</hi> of <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor</hi> gave to <hi>Auſtin</hi> the <hi>Monk, Anno</hi> 601. <hi>(viz.)</hi> that he and his acknowledged no <hi>Superiority</hi> in the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> over them, nor any <hi>Superiour</hi> but their own <hi>Arch-Biſhop Caer Leonis,</hi> or (as ſome will have it) <hi>Senovenſis, qui ſub Deo ſolus poſſitus fuit ſuper illos, ad ſuper videndum &amp; ad faciendum illos ſervare viam ſpiritualem,</hi> who alone was, under God, made an <hi>Overſeer</hi> or <hi>Biſhop</hi> to them, that he might make them obſerve the Spiritual way. Seing this ſtout <hi>Champion</hi> thus anſwered, it is propable that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62330:18"/>they were of the <hi>Primitive Inſtitution:</hi> And this I rather give credit to, becauſe, if the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> had then held the preſent Tenent of that Church, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that their City is the <hi>Spiritual Metropolis,</hi> and that their <hi>Biſhop</hi> is <hi>Caput Eccleſiae,</hi> our Predeceſſours would have acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>See,</hi> as they had been taught. But <hi>Baronius</hi> ſaith, that our <hi>Engliſh Biſhops</hi> are as <hi>Antient</hi> as thoſe of <hi>Rome,</hi> and it is probable they were.</p>
            <p>For this we have good proof, that at a <hi>Council</hi> held at <hi>Arles, Anno</hi> 314, we had three <hi>Biſhops,</hi> (viz.) <hi>Eborius de Civitate Eboraci Epiſcopus, Reſtitutus de Civitate Londini Epiſcopus, Eldelphius de Civitate Coloniae Londinenſium; &amp; exinde, Sacerdos Presbyter, Arminius Diaconus: Eborius Biſhop of</hi> York; <hi>Reſtitutus Biſhop of</hi> London; <hi>Eldelphius Biſhop of</hi> Colcheſter; and after them, <hi>Sacerdos a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter; Arminius a Deacon:</hi> Theſe ſubſcribed in this <hi>Council;</hi> here therefore I obſerve, that in the year 314, we had <hi>Biſhops, Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> the very Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment now in queſtion; and <hi>Romiſh</hi> they were not, (as I conceive) becauſe they then acknowledged not a <hi>Subordination</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> and becauſe <hi>Urban</hi> the Second called Learned <hi>Anſelme, Patriarcha Brittanniae,</hi> the <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch</hi> of <hi>Brittain:</hi> Therefore methinks it ſhould not now be queſtioned whether <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> be a <hi>Romiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique;</hi> but rather that it ſhould be confirmed as an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Ordinance,</hi> and as <hi>Antient</hi> as the firſt <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of Churches, and as a <hi>Calling</hi> appointed by the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> What more have we for <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of Infants? What more for our <hi>Lords Day</hi> or <hi>Sunday,</hi> but <hi>convincing Dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:62330:18"/>from the Scriptures, or the <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> and the Obſervation of the ſame in the Churches of God <hi>ſucceſſively</hi> to this very day? And yet we hold both theſe to be Sacred Ordinances, and of <hi>Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution;</hi> though they be both queſtioned by ſome men of the Reformed Churches, as <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is among ſome of Ours: The Caſe is alike, and as clear, (if not clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) for <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> that it had a <hi>Divine Inſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If what is formerly ſaid ſatisfie not, I will only uſe this Argument more, to prove that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is <hi>jure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino.</hi> If the <hi>Charge</hi> given, <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6, 14. be to <hi>Timothy perſonally,</hi> and be <hi>perpetual;</hi> then it is to <hi>One perſon</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Timothy</hi> and to the <hi>Succeſſours</hi> in his place; for <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> was Mortal, ſo that the <hi>perpetuity</hi> of the <hi>Charge</hi> muſt reach to all his <hi>Succeſſours</hi> until the Appearing of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> But the <hi>Charge</hi> is <hi>perſonal</hi> to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> and <hi>perpetual</hi> even to the Appearing of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> therefore it is to one <hi>perſon, (viz.)</hi> to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> and to his <hi>Succeſſours</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If it be here objected, that the <hi>Charge</hi> was given to <hi>Timothy,</hi> as elſewhere the Keys to <hi>Peter;</hi> and according to that which is ſaid, <hi>quod dixit Petro, dixit ceteris<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Apoſtolis,</hi> what was ſpoke to <hi>Peter,</hi> was ſpoke to the other <hi>Apoſtles</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, It is true; for, what was ſaid to <hi>Timothy,</hi> was ſaid <hi>ceteriſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Epiſcopis &amp; Succeſſoribus corum;</hi> both to other <hi>Biſhops</hi> and their <hi>Succeſſours,</hi> as Chriſt's giving the Keys to <hi>Peter,</hi> was to <hi>him</hi> and the other <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles;</hi> but not to all <hi>Diſciples, Deacons,</hi> and <hi>Widdows.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:62330:19"/>
            <p> To ſum up all: Since it appears that <hi>Epiſcopacy, Presbytery,</hi> and <hi>Diaconatus,</hi> are according to the <hi>practice</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles; Analogical</hi> to the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of the Jewiſh Church appointed by God, and eſtabliſht by <hi>Moſes;</hi> pointed at, and, in ſome ſort, <hi>deciphered</hi> in the <hi>New-Teſtament;</hi> and ſtrongly inſinuated by the <hi>Succeſſours</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> to have been received and practiſed by them, as commended to them by <hi>Divine Authority:</hi> Since theſe <hi>three Orders</hi> in our Church are derived ſo high, have continued ſo long, even from the <hi>Primitive</hi> times to this day, we may well conclude, that, as <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> ſo <hi>Biſhops</hi> are <hi>jure divino;</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, ſeeing <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is ſo generally confirmed, and hath been ſo conſtantly continued by the <hi>Aphſtles, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick men, Councils, Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Doctors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And much the rather I am induced thus (as I have ſaid) to judge of <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> becauſe the contrary part have not the like Proofs, Warrant, and Approbation for their <hi>Presbytery;</hi> and can bring no ſufficient and convincing <hi>Authority</hi> for a <hi>Quarterly</hi> or <hi>Yearly Preſident, joynt Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Lay-Elders</hi> uſurping <hi>Paſtoral</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopal Jurisdiction.</hi> And here in confidence of my Cauſe I add, That if they have any lawful <hi>General Council,</hi> or any <hi>Synod</hi> (except their own) which eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Church-Government by ſuch a <hi>Preſident, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters,</hi> and <hi>Lay-Elders</hi> as aforeſaid, I will renounce my Opinion, and yield the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>Now it concernes us very much to be well adviſed, and truly to judge of theſe Matters; becauſe it appears
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62330:19"/>in a Seditious <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> entituled <hi>the Prelates Pride,</hi> that the Author thereof, and ſuch as he is, care not what Government be eſtabliſhed, ſo that <hi>Popery</hi> (which we wiſh more rightly than they) may be aboliſht; <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy</hi> and the preſent Government (which how incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient it may be they know not) may be aboliſht; and they have Liberty and Toleration (which what ſettled <hi>State</hi> will permit) to profeſs what <hi>Religion</hi> they pleaſe to make choice of, and what ſhall beſt ſuit their own <hi>Intereſt,</hi> (the <hi>Card</hi> they commonly ſail by: So may we have as many <hi>Religions</hi> as there be at <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> and unpeople all our Plantations, by calling home many <hi>Phanatical Sciſmaticks,</hi> who, under colour of diſlike of the Church-Government here, have fallen out with our Religion, and framed to themſelves di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>Opinions</hi> (if not <hi>Religions</hi>) contrary to ours not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Form,</hi> but <hi>Reality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing then there is but <hi>one Lord, one Faith, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, one God,</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> of All; let us endeavour to keep the <hi>Unity</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> in the <hi>bond</hi> of <hi>Peace:</hi> That there may be <hi>one Body,</hi> and <hi>one Spirit,</hi> even as we are Called in <hi>one Hope</hi> of our Calling, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. Let us ſtick faſt to that one Truth which we are taught; and be ſtedfaſt in <hi>one Faith;</hi> and agree jointly with one accord, like Children of the ſame Father and Mother: Let us not looſe the Honour of our Church-Government, but reform the perſonal Errours, if any ſuch be; and ſinde <hi>Reformation</hi> ſignifies nothing elſe, but the reduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſetting Matters into the <hi>Form</hi> in which they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62330:20"/>were moſt <hi>perfect;</hi> let us conſtantly bold our ſelves to the <hi>Form</hi> kept and practiſed in the <hi>primitiver</hi> and <hi>pureſt Times,</hi> and in the Firſt and Second <hi>Centuries;</hi> in which we ſhall find the <hi>Order Epiſcopal, Presbyterial,</hi> and <hi>Diaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> obſerved, and ever ſince <hi>confirmed</hi> by <hi>National Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods,</hi> and <hi>Councils</hi> of our own, near 1400 years ago, (or 1000 at leaſt) and <hi>practiſed</hi> in many <hi>Succeſſions,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and ſince.</p>
            <p>Nothing now remains, but Prayers and Endeavours for the Continuance of the <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> of the <hi>preſent</hi> Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which is ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Antient <hi>Conſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Only now here I wiſh that we may ſave the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our dear and aged Mother, and puniſh her Sons, if any have diſhonoured her by <hi>pride, tyranny, covetouſneſs,</hi> or any other way; and that the Church and <hi>Common-wealth</hi> may hold ſuch <hi>Correſpondency,</hi> as they did in the days of <hi>David;</hi> and as Kings were <hi>nurſing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and Queens <hi>nurſing Mothers</hi> to the Church in her <hi>Infancy;</hi> ſo in her <hi>Age,</hi> ſhe may find Kings to ſupport her, if weak: And if any of her Children be like <hi>Eli</hi>'s, their <hi>Father</hi> may correct them, ſo that their <hi>Mother</hi> may not be diſhonoured and ruined.</p>
            <p>I conclude with that of St. <hi>Auguſtine, ſi quid tota ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia hodie frequent at per orbem, hoc quin ita ſit faciendum diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putare, inſolentiſſimae est inſaniae;</hi> if any thing at this day be of frequent uſe in the whole Church, to queſtion and diſpute whether it ought ſo to be, is a moſt inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Madneſs, <hi>Epist.</hi> 118; and that it is <hi>Arianiſm,</hi> to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62330:20"/>ſay, That <hi>Presbyters</hi> (in <hi>Common Acception</hi>) are <hi>equal</hi> to <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ſuch as were <hi>Succeſſours</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> and ſuch as St. <hi>Augustin</hi> himſelf was: This <hi>Epiphanius</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons it among the Antient <hi>Hereſies,</hi> and time hath not bettered it: And whether it reſembles and comes near the <hi>Antilogie</hi> of <hi>Korah</hi> or not, (my ſelf not being rigid and prone to cenſure) I leave to be determined by Others.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
